Guide to the Patrick H. Cain papers, 1783-1940 RL.00183
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Patrick H. Cain papers
1783-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cain, Patrick H.
RL.00183
6 Linear Feet
Merchant, tobacco merchant, landowner, distiller, and State Representative, from Mocksville and Settle (Davie Co.), N.C. Personal, legal, business, and financial papers of Patrick H. Cain and the Cain family, from Davie County, N.C. Included are letters describing life and social customs in Georgia; the education of women; student life at Normal College (later Trinity College, then Duke University) and at the University of North Carolina; Western migration; prices of products and services, the value of slaves, and the wages of freedmen; and the life of Confederate soldiers and military actions at First Manassas and Gettysburg. Legal papers consist of land grants, deeds, mortgages, arrests and summonses for debts, promissory notes, and material relating to the administration of various estates. Financial records include tax receipts and accounts. There is one volume of patient accounts, 1906-1925, belonging to Dr. John Cain. Correspondents include George Burgess Anderson, Francis Asbury, Samuel Ashe, Kemp P. Battle, John Joseph Bruner, D. R. Bruton, Lyman Copeland Draper, David Moffatt Furches, William H. Hayes, William Hill, Hamilton C. Jones, Leonidas Polk, Zebulon Vance, and Jonathan Worth.
Approx. 2,904 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Patrick H. Cain Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1957.
Biographical Note
Patrick H. Cain was born in 1815 in Davie County, N.C., the son of Daniel Cain and Elizabeth Hutchins. Patrick Cain married Susan Wilder Cheshire and had the following children: William Gaston, John Manley, Betty Ann, Millard Fillmore, Robert Lee.
Collection Overview
Personal, legal, business, and financial papers of the Cain family. Included are letters describing life and social customs in Georgia, 1824-1827; school life at girls' academies, 1843-1856, at Normal College (later Trinity College), 1855-1856, at a seminary, 1869, and at the University of North Carolina, 1871-1880; Western migration and Western lands; business methods; prices of products and services, the value of slaves, and wages and tenancy of freedmen; the life of Confederate soldiers, including accounts of military activities, especially First Manassas and Gettysburg, and comments on conditions in the army and on officers, Jefferson Davis, and Abraham Lincoln.
Legal papers consist of land grants, deeds, mortgages, arrests and summonses for debts, promissory notes, and material relating to the administration of various estates. There are broadsides concerning Jonathan Worth and W. W. Holden. Financial records consist of tax receipts; accounts, 1889-1895, kept in advertising booklets; and a ledger containing patient accounts, 1906-1925, belonging to Dr. John M. Cain, Patrick Cain's brother. There are many manuscript volumes in the collection, chiefly financial.
Correspondents include George Burgess Anderson, Francis Asbury, Samuel Ashe, Kemp P. Battle, John Joseph Bruner, D. R. Bruton, Lyman Copeland Draper, David Moffatt Furches, Will H. Hayes, William Hill, Hamilton C. Jones, Leonidas Polk, Zebulon Vance, and Jonathan Worth.
Related Material
Last Will and Testament of Daniel Cain of Davie County, NC, 1844, 1849 [Patrick Cain was the executor; contains names of slaves]
NC State Archives, Raleigh, N.C.
Merchants -- North Carolina; Merchants -- Accounting; Slave trade -- North Carolina; Probate law and practice -- North Carolina; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Slavery -- North Carolina; Women -- Education -- North Carolina; Daybooks; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Georgia -- Social life and customs; Southern States -- Economic conditions; Davie County (N.C.) -- Commerce; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Social conditions; Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Va., 1861; Freedmen -- North Carolina; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863; Migration, Internal -- United States; Cain, Patrick H.; Draper, Lyman Copeland, 1815-1891; Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.); Asbury, Francis, 1745-1816; Battle, Kemp P. (Kemp Plummer), 1831-1919; Vance, Zebulon Baird; Cain family; Polk, Leonidas, 1806-1864; Worth, Jonathan, 1802-1869
- Letters, 1824-1940
  - 1824-1878, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1879-1897, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1898-1912, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1913-1940 (Box 1)
- Legal Papers, 1783-1924
  - 1783-1827 (Box 1)
  - 1783-1827 oversize (Box 4)
  - 1828-1846 (Box 1)
  - 1847-1856 (Box 1)
  - 1857-1860, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1861-1876 (Box 1)
  - 1878-1896 (Box 1)
  - 1897-1924 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts, 1811-1940
  - 1811-1830s (Box 1)
  - 1840s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1850s, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1860s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1880s-1890s (Box 2)
  - 1890s (Box 2)
  - 1900-1909 (Box 2)
  - 1912-1940, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellany and Printed Material, 1841-1938
  - Miscellany and Printed Material, 1857-1938 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany and Printed material oversize, 1841 (Box 4)
- Volumes
  - Volumes, 1833-1935; 12 folders (Box 2-3)
  - Volumes, 1881-1885, 1891-1892 (Box 4)
  - Day Book, 1840-1844 (Box 5)
  - John M. Cain Ledger, 1906-1925 (Volume F:6868)